Seamus Heaney collection, 1972-1997
Emory University
Seamus Heaney collection, 1972-2005
Heaney, Seamus, 1939-
Manuscript Collection No.653
1 linear ft. (3 boxes) and 12 oversized papers (OP)
Collection of materials relating to Irish poet Seamus Heaney including correspondence, writings by Heaney, printed materials, and photographs.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Collection assembled from various sources.
Restrictions on access
Special restrictions apply: Series 4: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Researchers must contact MARBL in advance for access to audiovisual materials in this collection.
Biographical Note
Seamus Heaney was born on April 13, 1939, the eldest of nine children, to Margaret and Patrick Heaney, at the family farm, Mossbawn, northwest of Belfast in County Derry. He attended the local school at Anahorish until 1957 when he enrolled at Queens College, Belfast, where he studied English. After graduation he taught English at St. Joseph's College in Belfast.
While at St. Joseph's he began to write, publishing work in university magazines under the pseudonym Incertus. During that time, he joined a poetry workshop organized by Philip Hobsbaum. In 1965, in connection with the Belfast Festival, he published Eleven Poems, and in August of that year he married Marie Devlin. The following year he became a lecturer in modern English literature at Queens College; his first son, Michael, was born; and Faber and Faber published Death of a Naturalist. This collection earned him the Eric Gregory Award, the Cholmondeley Award, the Somerset Maugham Award, and the Geoffrey Faber Memorial Prize. Marie and Seamus Heaney's second son, Christopher, was born in 1968.
Door Into the Dark, published in 1969, was a Poetry Book Society Choice for the year. In 1970-1971, Heaney was guest lecturer at the University of California, Berkeley. He returned to Northern Ireland in 1971, and in 1972 he resigned his lectureship at Queens College, moved his family to Glanmore, in County Wicklow, and published Wintering Out. In 1973 his daughter Catherine Ann was born. During this year he also received the Denis Devlin Award and the Writer in Residence Award from the American Irish Foundation. In 1975 North was published, winning the E.M. Forster Award and the Duff Cooper Memorial Prize. During these years at Glanmore, Heaney also gave many readings in the United States and England and edited two poetry anthologies.
In 1975 Heaney began teaching at Carysfort College in Dublin, and in 1976 he and his family moved to Sandymount in the city. In 1979 Heaney published Field Work and in 1980 Selected Poems and Preoccupations. In 1981 he gave up his position at Carysfort to become visiting professor at Harvard. In 1982 he won the Bennett Award and Queens University awarded him an honorary Doctor of Letters. He co-founded Field Day company with the playwright Brian Friel and others in 1983. Station Island, his first collection in five years, was published in 1984. During that year he was elected Boylston Professor of Rhetoric and Oratory at Harvard. That same year his mother died.
In 1988 Seamus Heaney visited Emory University where he inaugurated the Richard Ellmann Lectures in Modern Literature. These lectures were collected and published as The Place of Writing in 1989. In 1991 Heaney published a new collection Seeing Things, followed by the Redress of Poetry in 1995. In the fall of that year, Heaney was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of materials relating to Seamus Heaney from 1972-2005 including, writings by Heaney, printed materials, photographs and correspondence. The manuscript writings in the collection include multiple drafts of "Fosterage," a two-page typescript on Michael McLaverty (published as an introduction to McLaverty's Collected Stories in 1978), a manuscript of a talk on Wordsworth's Prelude which Heaney wrote for Irish radio around 1974, and settings copies of the poems "Bog Queen," "Punishment," "The Grauballe Man," and "Kinship," with editor's markings and corrections in Heaney's hand. There is also a manuscript of a poem "For Daisy," written on the occasion of Daisy Garnett's christening. Heaney gave the keynote address during Emory University's 2003 commencement and a typescript draft with revisions in his hand is also included in this section.
The collection also includes printed promotional posters, programs, a small group of photographs, and a DVD of an interview with Heaney.
The restricted correspondence consists of letters from Seamus Heaney to Sebastian Barker from 1981-1991 and relate to proposed readings, an essay Heaney was writing on Patrick Kavanagh, and Barker's proposal that Heaney serve as President of the Poetry Society. Additional correspondence with Mrs. Parker (1976) and "Robert" (1978) relate to items found in the writing series of this collection and the J. Howard Woolmer correspondence relates to the publication of Stern, a poem in memory of Ted Hughes.
Arrangement Note
Organized into five series: (1) Writings by Seamus Heaney, (2) Printed material, (3) Photographs, (4) Restricted correspondence, and (5) Audiovisual materials.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Barker, Sebastian.; Kavanagh, P. J. (Patrick Joseph), 1931-; McLaverty, Michael.; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850.
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish literature--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.
Geographic Names
Ireland.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Video recordings.
Occupation
Poet.
Related Materials in This Repository
Ciaran Carson papers, Peter Fallon/The Gallery Press Collection, Seamus Heaney papers, Ted Hughes papers, Thomas Kinsella papers, Michael Longley papers, Derek Mahon papers, Medbh McGuckian papers, Charles Montieth papers, Paul Muldoon papers, Edna O'Brien papers, Desmond O'Grady papers, Frank Ormsby papers, Tom Paulin papers, and James Simmons papers
Description of Series
- Writings by Seamus Heaney, Series 1; Box 1: folders 1-12
  - "For Daisy Garnett," holograph manuscript, 2pp. Poem written for the christening of Polly Devlin's (Garnett) daughter Daisy Garnett. [See also Series 3, Photographs: "Polly Garnett and three children," and Series 4, Restricted correspondence: "Mrs. Parker"] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Four Poems: "Bog Queen," "Punishment," "The Grauballe Man," "Kinship," setting copy with editor's markings and corrections in Heaney's hand, 7 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Fosterage" [variant titles "Stylist," "To Michael McLaverty," and "Friendship's Garland"], multiple holograph and typescript drafts, 10 pp. [See also Series 4, Restricted correspondence: "Robert"] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Introduction" [from Michael McLaverty's Collected Stories], photocopied typescript, 2 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - James Joyce Quarterly, Spring 1974, corrected guest editor's galley proofs. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - James Joyce Quarterly, Spring 1974, revised page proofs. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Leavings," typescript with corrections in Heaney's hand (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Placeless Heaven: Another Look at Kavanagh," 13 pp. photocopy typescript, Series 4, Restricted correspondence: Sebastian Barker, 26 March 1987] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Prelude" [on William Wordsworth], holograph manuscript, 11 pp. with 8 pp. of typed quotations from "The Prelude" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Strange Fruit," multiple holograph and typescript drafts, 12 pp (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Speeches/Addresses
  - Commencement Address, University of Pennsylvania, 30 May 2000, reprint in University of Pennsylvania Almanac (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commencement Keynote Address, Emory University, 12 May 2003, TS with corrections, 9pp. [also includes signed copy of Commencement program] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Printed material, Series 2; Box 2: folders 13-18; OP1-3 and 5-12
  - Book Covers
  - Keeping Going, cover for collection of poems to be published in 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Postcards
  - Irish Nobel Prizewinners for Literature, Seamus Heaney featuring "The Railway Children" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Posters
  - Beowulf, promotional poster for Faber and Faber (Box OP7)
  - The Cure at Troy, promotional poster for the Abbey Theatre production (Box OP1)
  - Know the Sign of a Poet, promotional poster for Faber and Faber poetry books, printed signatures of 34 poets, including Seamus Heaney (Box OP5)
  - Seamus Heaney, Faber and Faber promotional poster for Heaney's Nobel Prize for literature 1995 and Whitbread Book of the Year for The Spirit Level [2 copies] (Box OP9)
  - Seamus Heaney, Nobel Prize promotional poster, 1995 (Box OP3)
  - Stations, promotional poster for Ulster Youth Theatre performance at Saranmilis College based on Station Island by Seamus Heaney, 7-11 November [19??] (Box OP8)
  - The Spirit Level, promotional poster for Faber and Faber edition (Box OP2)
  - Sweeney's Flight, promotional poster for photographic exhibition, Rachel Giese, photographer with descriptive captions by Seamus Heaney, n.d. (Box OP6)
  - Programs
  - The Burial at Thebes, program for Nottingham Playhouse Theatre Company production, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Cure at Troy, program for Harvard Repertory Theatre production, n.d. Includes "Sweet Talk and Miracles: notes on The Cure at Troy," by Heaney (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Love and War" reading to benefit the Arvon Foundation, program, 2 March 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The Poet and the Piper," concert program for Belfast Waterfront Hall, 10 November 2001 [Seamus Heaney, Liam O'Flynn and the works of John B. Vallely] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prospectuses
  - Squarings, prospectus, The Arion Press, 2003 [with envelope] (Box OP10)
  - Articles
  - "Bags of Enlightenment," [Partners in Poetry: Heaney on Hughes], The Guardian, Review section, 25 October 2003 (Box OP11)
  - "Seamus Heaney toi Nobelin Eurooppaan," Helsigin Sanomat, Kulttuuri section, 6 October 1995 (Box OP12)
- Photographs, Series 3; Box 1: folders 19-26; OP4
  - Heaney alone
  - Seamus Heaney at Harvard, Fall 1983, 6 black and white photographs (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Seamus Heaney at home of Ron Schuchard, 1988, 2 photographs (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Seamus Heaney, large black and white photograph, n.d (Box OP4)
  - Heaney with others
  - Seamus Heaney and Ted Walker, color photograph, 12 August 1972. Pasted on verso of half-title of Death of a Naturalist [PR6058.E2 D401 1969] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Richard Ellmann and Seamus Heaney at the Hill of Howth, [1982], 4 color photographs (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Seamus Heaney with Marie Heaney in the background at the Poetry Library, London, 1990, 1 black and white photograph by John Minihan (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Seamus Heaney with Bernard O'Donoghue outside Kenny's Bookshop, Galway, Ireland, 1998, 1 black and white photograph by John Minihan (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Seamus Heaney and Joseph Brodsky, n.d., 1 color photograph by John Minihan (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Seamus Heaney at dedication of Gerard Manley Hopkins memorial, three black and white photographs by Bill Storey, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Others
  - Polly Devlin (Garnett) and her 3 children on the occasion of her daughter Daisy's christening, color photograph, n.d. [See also Series 4, Restricted Correspondence: "Mrs. Parker" and Series 1: Writings: "For Daisy Garnett"] (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Restricted correspondence, Series 4; Box 2
  Restrictions on access
  Special restrictions apply: Letters from Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  - Sebastian Barker
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, 19 February 1981, ALS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, 19 July 1982, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, 24 February 1985, ALS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, [25 January 1987], ACS (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, 26 March 1987, TLS, 1 p. [See also Series 1, Writings: "The Placeless Heaven: Another Look at Kavanagh"] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, [16 April 1990], ACS (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - SH to Sebastian Barker, 6 December 1991, TLS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Parker
  - SH to Mrs. Parker, 26 November 1976, ALS, 1 p. [See also Series 1, Writings: "For Daisy Garnett" and Series 3: Photographs: "Polly Devlin (Garnet)"] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rolando Pieraccini
  - SH to Rolando Pieraccini, 28 March 1989, ALS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - SH to Rolando Pieraccini, 20 June 1989, ALS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SH to Rolando Pieraccini, 16 January 1990, ALS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SH to Rolando Pieraccini, 20 January 1990, TLS, 1 p. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SH to Rolando Pieraccini, 27 February 1990, TLS, 1 p. with envelope (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Robert"
  - SH to "Robert", 30 May 1978, ALS, 1 p. [See also Series 3, Writings: "Fosterage"] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - J. Howard Woolmer [regarding publication of Stern, a poem in memory of Ted Hughes]
  - 20 October 2004-8 January 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Audiovisual material, Series 5; Box 3
  - "Joyce, Yeats and Wilde: Seamus Heaney and Richard Ellmann in Conversation," Radio Telefis Eireann, July 15, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Quis Est Deus?: Bridges of the Spirit" [includes interview with Seamus Heaney], January 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)